Guide to the Records of the American Defense Society 1915-1942 (bulk 1918-1920; 1935-1939) MS 14
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
American Defense Society Records
1915-1942 (bulk 1918-1920; 1935-1939)
MS 14
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
9.25 Linear feet (22 boxes)
This collection documents the views, aims, and internal workings of the American Defense Society, an early twentieth-century nationalist organization, based in New York City. The material dates from 1915 to 1942, and concerns many of the political, ideological, religious, and social debates and events of the time period. Nearly half of the American Defense Society Records consists of correspondence, including incoming and copies of outgoing letters, as well as internal communications among board members, officers, and members. In addition, the collection contains much printed material, some of which were published by the society. Also included is material that documents the society's internal organization, and newspaper clippings collected by ADS.
Provenance
Donation, Charles Stewart Davison, 1942
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Historical Note
1915 The American Defense Society, Inc. (ADS) is founded in New York City, in response to the sinking of the Lusitania, as a national "aggressive, non-partisan society having for its sole object the 'adequate national defense of the United States of America.'" ["The American Defense Society: History, Purpose and Accomplishments," 1918] Its board members and officers include prominent local businessmen and professionals. Theodore Roosevelt serves on the Advisory Board, and is later named Honorary President.
1916-1918 ADS advocates, among other policies, universal military service for American males, the suppression of "treasonable orators" and newspapers, the abolition of the teaching of German and the publication of German newspapers in the U.S., the unconditional surrender of Germany, and a boycott of German goods.
1917 Nov. 2 Anti-Disloyalty mass meeting is held at Carnegie Hall, where ADS calls for the expulsion of Robert LaFollette from the Senate and condemns William Randolph Hearst as a traitor.
1918 June New York attorney Charles Stewart Davison becomes Chairman of the Board of Trustees.
1918 ADS opposes "Pro-Germans, Socialists, Pacifists, Anti-Militarists, Conscientious Objectors, Anarchists, I.W.W.'s, so-called Friends of Irish Freedom and other organizations." [ADS "Hand Book," 1918]
1918 ADS forms Vigilance Corps around the U.S., whose purpose is to register "Alien Enemies, Pro-Germans, and Disloyal Americans."
[1918] ADS committees include Anti-Disloyalty Committee, Teachers Loyalty Committee.
1919 Honorary ADS President Theodore Roosevelt issues what would be his last public statement, "Keep up the Fight for Americanism," for an ADS mass meeting. The society inaugurates a campaign to distribute portraits of Roosevelt to organizations and schools throughout the U.S.
1920 ADS endorses Warren G. Harding for president, ending its claim to non-partisanship.
1920 Aug. Davison resigns as Chairman of Board, remains in ADS as an Honorary Chairman; Elon Huntington Hooker, head of Hooker Chemical Company, is nominated chairman.
[1920] ADS distributes pamphlets entitled "Protocols and World Revolution," that reference the anti-Semitic publication "The Protocols of the Elders of Zion."
1922 ADS campaigns include bringing Herrin Massacre participants to justice (for the murders of strikebreakers), and increasing congressional appropriation for defense.
1923 ADS holds two immigration restriction conferences; other campaigns include aviation awareness, and distribution of copies of the Constitution.
1924 ADS publishes Reds in America.
1926 A dispute with the ACLU involves pacifist organizations holding meetings in NYC public schools.
1924-1929 ADS continues its Constitution distribution campaign, advocating preparedness, discussing immigration, opposing pacifism and radicalism, and distributing Theodore Roosevelt portraits.
1929-1935 Activities are curtailed, the society suffers from financial troubles. ADS focuses on "an aggressive opposition to revolutionary activities," and anti-communism.
1930 Charles Stewart Davison and ADS trustee Madison Grant publish The Alien in Our Midst, or "Selling Our Birthright for a Mess of Pottage": The Written Views of a Number of Americans (Present and Former) on Immigration and Its Results (not an ADS publication).
1935 Efforts are made to reinvigorate ADS.
1937 ADS campaigns include opposition to FDR's Supreme Court expansion proposal.
1938 Death of board chairman Elon Huntington Hooker.
1942 Nov. Death of Charles Stewart Davison.
1942-1956 ADS presumably continues, is last listed in New York City directories in 1956.
Addresses in New York:
19[15]- Nov. 1, 1917: 303 Fifth Ave.
Nov. 1, 1917- [1918]: 44 E. 23rd St.
[1919-1920]: 1133 Broadway
[1920-1923]: 116 E. 24th St.
[1925-1937]: 154 Nassau St.
[1937-19??]: 225 Fifth Ave.
Scope and Content Note
This collection documents the views, aims, and internal workings of the American Defense Society, an early twentieth-century nationalist organization, based in New York City. The material dates from 1915 to 1942, and concerns many of the political, ideological, religious, and social debates and events of the time period. Popular topics of discussion include the first world war, preparedness, sedition and disloyalty, labor, immigration restriction, the Soviet Union and Bolshevism, socialism, civil liberties, the New Deal, FDR, and Judaism.
Nearly half of the American Defense Society Records consists of correspondenceâ??incoming and copies of outgoing letters, as well as internal communications among board members, officers, and members. In addition, the collection contains much printed material, especially pamphlets, periodicals, circulars, and newsletters, some of which were published by the society. Also included is material that documents the society's internal organization, such as meeting minutes, resolutions, committee lists, and financial records. Newspaper clippings collected by ADS concern topics of interest to the society and detail some of its activities.
Please take care when using this collection. Much of the material, such as outgoing copies of correspondence, is on brittle newsprint paper.
Arrangement
Within each series, material is arranged, for the most part, in chronological order.
The American Defense Society Records are arranged into the following four series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1916-1942
Series II. Organizational Material, 1917-1941
Series III. Printed Material, 1915-1942
Series IV. Newspaper Clippings, 1917-1938, undated
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The Library has pamphlets published by ADS, and not found in this collection. See:
"The American Defense Society: Its Aims, Its History, Its Officers," 1941
William Guggenheim, "Peace Reflections: The Waning Day - The New Dawn" [1919]
The Library also has:
William T. Hornaday, Awake! America: Object Lessons and Warnings (NY, 1918); published under the auspices of ADS
Madison Grant and Charles Stewart Davison, eds., The Founders of the Republic on Immigration Naturalization and Aliens (NY, 1928)
Charles Stewart Davison, "The Lusitania Murders and The Responsibilities of Presidents" (NY?, 1915)
Davison, Charles Stewart, 1855-1942; Grant, Madison, 1865-1937; Harding, Warren G. (Warren Gamaliel), 1865-1923; Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951; Hooker, Elon Huntington, 1869-1938; Industrial Workers of the World; Mooney, Thomas J., 1882-1942; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919; Aliens--United States; Annual reports.; Anti-communist movements--United States; Anti-Jewish propaganda; Clippings.; Conservatism--United States; Correspondence.; Ephemera.; Financial records.; Immigration opponents--United States; Internal security--United States; Leaflets.; Minutes.; Nativism; Nativistic movements--United States; Pamphlets.; Patriotic societies--United States; Photographs.; Posters.; Press releases.; Programs.; Protocols of the wise men of Zion; Radicalism--United States; United States--Emigration and immigration; United States--Politics and government--20th century; World War, 1914-1918
- Series I. Correspondence, 1916-1942
  Scope and Contents note
  This series is arranged chronologically and includes incoming, copies of outgoing, and internal ADS correspondence (among board members, officers, and members). Also included are letters to and from Charles Stewart Davison that do not deal directly with ADS.
  In general, attachments were kept with their respective correspondence. However, original ADS organizational material attached to letters, such as meeting minutes, resolutions, and financial reports, was removed to Series II, and a preservation photocopy was filed in its place. Newspaper clippings were also copied, and removed to Series IV.
  Letters from 1916 to 1917 deal with World War I, ADS meetings and internal society matters, and politics. There are also numerous responses to ADS's "ten proposals" from business leagues, leaders, retail associations and chambers of commerce around the country.
  Topics in correspondence from 1918 include the case of Thomas Mooney (the labor activist accused of bombing a patriotic march), the I.W.W., 'subversive' meetings, conditions in the U.S. Army (sickness, pay), William Randolph Hearst (his disloyalty), the ADS campaign/boycott against German goods and the teaching of German in schools, German atrocities, the impending post-war settlement with Germany ("unconditional surrender"), the situation in Russia, sedition and disloyalty, and immigration restriction. Internal correspondence discusses ADS proposals and operational matters including events, aims, salaries, campaigns, finances, and the women's committee. Also included are correspondence from the DC bureau of ADS, correspondence with artist Edwin Howland Blashfield regarding his stamp design for the society, and letters from members of congress. One set of correspondence with the Auburn Bureau, filed together in a report, deals with an ADS editorial and a threat of libel suit.
  Topics from 1919 include the post-war future of ADS, the death of Theodore Roosevelt, the Citizens Committee of Welcome for U.S. soldiers, immigration restriction, labor, socialism, Bolshevism, and William Randolph Hearst.
  1920 correspondence discusses the future of ADS and its financial troubles, Bolshevism, subversive behavior, immigration, labor strikes, the situation in Ireland, internal ADS matters such as meetings, finances, and campaigns i.e. Roosevelt portraits, lawsuits, the distribution of "Protocols and World Revolution," and personal matters of staff members. Numerous letters from members concern the 1920 presidential election and the society's support of candidate Warren G. Harding.
  Topics in correspondence from 1921-1928 include the Mooney case, socialism in American colleges and student radicals, post-war Germany, Sinn Fein, Bolshevism, the AFL and unions, 'red and pink organizations,' the 1922 Herrin massacre, the "Protocols," Hearst, world politics, immigration and labor, the 'youth movement,' the Soviet Union and communism, race and crime, aviation, the ACLU, Judaism, Catholicism, and the presidential candidacy of Al Smith. Immigration restriction is a prominent topic of discussion from 1923-1928. Letters also deal with internal ADS matters including the street speaking campaign, the society's debt and financial difficulties, and libel suits against ADS.
  Correspondence from 1929 to 1934 concerns ADS debt and finances, distribution of anti-communist pamphlets, the Socialist party, and Davison's legal matters.
  Topics from 1935 to 1942 include the revival and reorganization of ADS, the society's debt and first meetings, Franklin Delano Roosevelt, immigration, FDR's putative Jewish lineage, congressional bills, Judaism and Jews, the 1936 and 1940 elections, the 1937 Supreme Court controversy, communism, foreign affairs, Soviet matters, the US government, religion, financial theories and banking, the House Un-American Activities Committee, US involvement in the WW II, strikes, grand juries, and national defense. Much of the material for these years is Charles Stewart Davison's letters to editors and senators about world politics or correspondence of Davison that does not deal directly with ADS.
  - Correspondence, 1916 June-1917 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1917 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1917 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Jan.-Feb. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Mar.-Apr. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1918 May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1918 June (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1918 July 1-11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1918 July 12-26 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1918 July 27-31 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Aug. 1-13 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Aug. 14-24 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Aug. 26-31 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Sept. 1-9 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Sept. 10-16 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Sept. 17-21 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Sept. 22-31 [sic] (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Oct. 1-9 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Oct. 10-15 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Oct. 16-19 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Oct. 20-23 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Oct. 24-31 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence (with Auburn Bureau), 1918 Aug.-Oct. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Nov. 1-8 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Nov. 9-15 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Nov. 16-30 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1918 Dec. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1919 Jan. 1-9 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1919 Jan. 10-16 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1919 Jan. 17-23 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1919 Jan. 24-31; Feb.-Mar (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1919 Apr.-June (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1919 July-Aug. 2 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1919 Aug. 4-Sept. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1919 Oct.-Nov. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1919 Dec. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Jan.-Feb. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Mar. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Apr. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1920 May (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1920 June (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1920 July (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Aug. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Sept. 1-14 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Sept. 15-30 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Oct. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Nov. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1920 Dec. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1921 Jan. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1921 Feb. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1921 Mar. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1921 Apr. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1921 May-June (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1921 July-Sept. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1921 Oct.-Dec. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1922 Jan.-May (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1922 June-July (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1922 Aug.-Dec. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1923 Jan.-Feb. (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1923 Mar.-June (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1923 Aug.-Dec. (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1924 Jan.-June (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1924 July-Dec. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, [1919-1924] (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1925 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1926 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1929 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1930 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1932 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1934 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1935 Jan.-Sept. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1935 Oct.-Dec. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1936 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1937 Jan.-June (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1937 July-Dec. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1938 Jan.-Mar. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1938 Apr. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1938 May-July (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1938 Aug.-Dec. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1940 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1941 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Loose envelopes (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Series II. Organizational Material, 1917-1941
  This series contains material that documents the daily operations of ADS including board and committee meeting minutes, schedules, programs, and notices; resolutions, proposals, editorials, press releases (often multiple drafts of); committee member and candidate lists; reports from outside sources on various topics; "operators reports" (purportedly inside information on subversive activities, personages and meetings); legal material; financial material (statements, receipts, reports); notes; memos; phone messages; calling and business cards, addresses, and photographs.
  Organizational material is arranged chronologically. Financial material, phone message slips, calling and business cards, and address slips are filed separately. Attachments were kept with material, usually memorandums; newspaper clippings were photocopied and moved to Series IV.
  Included in this series are three photographs of a woman, presumably an ADS Women's Committee member, soliciting signatures on a petition against the German press ([1918]). An additional photograph depicts what appears to be a mural of FDR and other individuals from the 1930s.
  - Organizational Material, 1917 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Organizational Material, 1918 Jan.-June (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Organizational Material, 1918 July-Oct. (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Organizational Material, 1918 Nov.-Dec. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Organizational Material, [1918] (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Organizational Material, [1918] (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Organizational Material, 1919 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Organizational Material, [1919] (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Organizational Material: Financial Records, 1917-1919 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Organizational Material: Notes, [1917-1919] (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Organizational Material: Calling and Business Cards/Address Slips, 1917-1919 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Organizational Material: Phone Message Slips, 1917-1919 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Organizational Material: Photographs, [1918] (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Organizational Material, 1920 Jan.-Aug. (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Organizational Material, 1920 Sept.-Dec. (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Organizational Material, 1921 Jan.-Apr. (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Organizational Material, 1921 May-Dec. (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Organizational Material, 1922 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Organizational Material, 1923 Jan.-Apr. (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Organizational Material, 1923 May-Dec. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Organizational Material, 1924 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Organizational Material, [1920-1924] (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Organizational Material, 1925-1927 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Organizational Material, [1920-1927] (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Organizational Material: Financial Records, 1920-1925 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Organizational Material: Calling and Business Cards, 1920-1925 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Organizational Material: Phone Message Slips, 1920-1928 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Organizational Material, 1931-1935 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Organizational Material, 1936-1937 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Organizational Material, 1938-1941 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Organizational Material, [1930-1939] (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Organizational Material: Financial Records, 1930-1939 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Organizational Material: Phone Message Slips/Calling and Business Cards, 1930-1939 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Organizational Material: Photograph, [1930s] (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Organizational Material: Fragments/Blank Pages, Undated (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Series III. Printed Material, 1915-1942
  This series contains printed material, including printed items not clearly attached to correspondence.
  - Subseries 1. Printed Material: ADS, 1916-1942
    Contains printed material of ADS such as annual reports/programs, circulars, pamphlets, mailings, handbooks, booklets, press releases, newsletters, programs, ephemera, ads for publications, and one poster. Topics include WW I (German war crimes, Turkey, peace terms, disease in the army), alien socialism, Russia, Bolshevism, immigration, sedition, communism, the ACLU, labor, 'Americanism.' ADS annual reports include detailed lists of material distributed each year.
    Included in this series are copies of the ADS Handbook and "The American Defense Society: History, Purpose and Accomplishments" (both 1918).
    Ephemera includes tickets, invites, notices, and programs for ADS meetings and dinners; also advertisements for ADS publications.
    - Printed Material: ADS, Annual Reports/Programs, 1919, 1922-1929, 1937-1939, 1941-1942 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Printed Material: ADS, 1916-1917 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Printed Material: ADS; Circulars, Pamphlets, Mailings, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Printed Material: ADS; Handbooks, History, Vigilance Corps., 1918 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Printed Material: ADS; Booklets, various topics, 1918, [1918] (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Printed Material: ADS; Booklets, various topics, 1918, [1918] (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material: ADS, Publication Samples, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Printed Material: ADS, Press Releases, 1918 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Printed Material: ADS, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Printed Material: ADS, American Defense newsletter, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Printed Material: ADS, Programs for American Defense Week, "American Day" meeting, 1917, 1919 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Printed Material: ADS, 1920-1921 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Printed Material: ADS, 1922-1924 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Printed Material: ADS, Press Releases, 1924 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Printed Material: ADS, 1925-1928 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Printed Material: ADS, 1937-1942 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Printed Material: ADS, Ephemera, 1917-1919, 1924, 1937-1939 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Printed Material: ADS, Promotional Poster, [1920] (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Printed Material: ADS, Undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Subseries 2. Printed Material: Outside Sources
    This subseries contains newsletters, printed speeches, pamphlets, reprints, poetry, publications, lectures, leaflets, ephemera and posters from a variety of individuals and organizations. Also included are copies of various periodicals. While the majority of this material shares a similar viewpoint with ADS, the society also acquired publications of groups it opposed, i.e. the Communist Party, and anarchists.
    Printed material from 1915-18 deals with World War I, the post-war settlement with Germany, Bolshevism, Russia, and the Thomas Mooney case. Material from 1919 to 1923 concerns Bolshevism, Russia, Germany, crime, communism, labor unions, the I.W.W., Ireland, congressional bills, Henry Ford and Judaism, the Herrin massacre, and immigration. Included are copies of Soviet Russia, "The Woman Patriot," The Rebel Worker, The Gentile Tribune, and the Liberator.